Imagine you're driving home from work on a Tuesday.
Right.
It's a totally normal commute.
Yeah, exactly.
You've taken this exact route like a thousand times.
You hit the highway, take your exit, make all the familiar turns, and you pull into your driveway.
Then you put the car in park, turn off the engine, and suddenly you realize you have absolutely no memory of the last 10 minutes.
Oh, yeah.
The classic autopilot.
Right.
Your mind was completely somewhere else.
Like you were thinking about a meeting or, you know, planning dinner.
Yet somehow you navigated a two-ton machine through traffic, obeyed all the traffic lights, and safely arrived at your exact destination.
It's actually terrifying when you really stop to think about it.
It is.
We all experience this, and we usually just write it off as, well, muscle memory or habit.
But what if I told you that the mathematics your brain just used to safely drive that car, the literal math is the exact same equation a computer uses to sort a massive database.
Yeah, which sounds crazy on its face.
And even more bizarrely, what if it's the exact same equation a quantum particle uses to navigate through space?
I mean, it sounds like complete science fiction when you frame it that way.
We are so deeply conditioned to separate biology, computer science, and, you know, fundamental physics into these totally isolated little boxes.
Right.
They don't touch.
Exactly.
But the mathematical bridge connecting them isn't just some neat metaphor.
It is a literal structural reality.
And that is exactly the journey we are going on today.
Because I know you, listening to this right now, you aren't here for some superficial summary.
No, definitely not.
You have that drive to gain deep fundamental knowledge.
You want the actual architecture of how reality works, but, you know, you don't want to get buried in this avalanche of totally unreadable academic jargon.
Which is very easy to do with this topic, trust me.
Oh, for sure.
So our mission today is to take a single, seemingly mundane concept, a computer science trick, really, invented in the 1950s called dynamic programming, and we're going to unpack it completely.
By the end of this hour, this little computational trick is going to completely rewrite how you understand physics, the nature of human consciousness, and incredibly even global economics.
And the source material we're using to make this leap is, well, it's a text that will likely be debated for decades.
It's intense.
Very.
It's a 2026 monograph by an independent researcher named Flickshun.
Just the title alone is a massive mouthful.
I have it right here.
It's called Recursive Admissibility, Dynamic Programming as Field Theory in the Relativistic Scalar Vector Plenum.
Rolls right off the tongue.
Right.
Okay, let's unpack this.
We are going to strip away the intimidating calculus and the dense vocabulary, and we are going to translate this really radical framework into clear, relatable, aha moments.
We need to figure out the how and the why behind all these massive claims.
Exactly.
But before we get to the whole reality is geometry stuff, we need to set a baseline.
Yeah, we have to look at how standard textbooks treat dynamic programming, which we'll probably just call DP from here on out.
DP.
Yeah.
So if you take a computer science 101 class, DP is taught purely as a computational shortcut.
Right.
It's framed as this clever way to save a computer's processing power by just making sure it never calculates the exact same thing twice.
A memory hack.
Essentially, yes.
But Fliction's entire thesis is that treating DP as just a memory hack misses the fundamental truth of what the algorithm actually is.
That's not just code.
No.
Fliction argues that DP is a universal geometric law.
It's the raw mathematical expression of how optimal trajectories evolve across any landscape at all.
Whether that landscape is physical space or cognitive learning or, you know, an economic market.
Exactly.
So to understand what this algorithm actually does in a normal computer, we have to go back to the Rand Corporation in the 1950s.
Right, to a mathematician named Richard Bellman.
Yeah.
He coined the term dynamic programming, and he built it on something called the principle of optimality.
Let's define this clearly for the listener.
What is this principle, basically?
The principle of optimality is, well, it's an incredibly elegant piece of logic.
Bellman stated that an optimal path, meaning the absolute most efficient way to get from a starting state to a goal state, is made entirely out of optimal subpaths.
Okay, let's ground that a bit.
Say I'm looking at a map, right, and I want to drive from city A to city C.
Okay.
And let's say the absolute fastest route requires me to drive through city B, which is right in the middle.
Are you saying that the specific roads I took from city A to city B must be the fastest possible way to get to city B?
That is the absolute core of it.
Think about the alternative for a second.
Suppose your route from A to C was the fastest overall, but that first leg from A to B was somehow slow and inefficient.
Like I took a really bad detour.
Right.
If that were true, you could simply replace that inefficient A to B leg with a faster one, and suddenly your total trip to C would be even faster.
Oh, I see.
Therefore, an optimal global solution simply cannot contain any suboptimal local fragments.
The perfection has to go all the way down to the individual puzzle pieces.
Right.
Optimality is inherently recursive.
It nests inside itself.
Yeah, and this recursive structure is exactly what allows a computer to take a massive, globally complex problem, one that would literally take billions of years to brute force, and break it down into tiny, solvable, local fragments.
And the paper calls out two specific requirements for this to actually work, what it calls the twin pillars of standard dynamic programming.
Yes.
The first is what we just talked about, right?
Optimal substructure.
The big solution is made of perfect little solutions.
But the second pillar is overlapping subproblems.
And here is where I want to push back just a little bit.
Okay, go ahead.
Because this sounds an awful lot like the standard divide and conquer method.
You know, if I have a messy stack of files, I divide the stack in half, I sort one half, I sort the other half, and then I merge them together.
Isn't that the exact same thing?
It's a really common confusion, actually.
And Flitchinon specifically uses sorting algorithms to illustrate the difference here.
When you divide a stack of files in half to sort them a method known in computer science as merge sort, you are indeed breaking a big problem into smaller ones.
Right.
But those smaller problems are completely independent of each other.
The files in the left stack have absolutely nothing to do with the files in the right stack.
Oh.
You sort them in total isolation.
Correct.
They don't interact at all until the very end.
But dynamic programming is only necessary, and frankly, only works when the subproblems heavily overlap.
Overlap how?
Well, the text contrasts merge sort with a problem called matrix chain multiplication.
Let's walk through that slowly, because matrix math can definitely scare people off, including me.
Huh.
Fair enough.
We don't need to do any actual math to understand the structure here.
Imagine you have a long chain of matrices you need to multiply together.
Okay.
Because of the rules of linear algebra, you can group them in different ways.
You can multiply the first two and then multiply the result by the third.
Yeah.
Or you can multiply the second and third together and then multiply the first by that result.
The final answer is mathematically identical, but the actual number of calculations your computer has to perform changes drastically depending on how you group them.
So you obviously want to find the most efficient way to group them before you actually make the computer do the heavy lifting of the math.
Yes, but to find the most efficient grouping for a chain of, say, 10 matrices, you have to test splitting the chain at every single possible point.
And here is where the overlap happens.
Exactly.
If you test splitting the chain at matrix 5, you have to calculate the optimal way to multiply matrices 1 through 5.
But then, if you test splitting the chain at matrix 6, you again have to calculate the optimal way to multiply matrices 1 through 5, just as a subcomponent of 1 through 6.
Ah, I get it now.
If you are just using a naive divide-and-conquer approach, your computer is going to calculate the best way to multiply matrices 1 through 5 over and over and over again for every different global permutation it tries.
And the redundancy is catastrophic.
The number of calculations just explodes exponentially.
The computer is doing the exact same homework assignment a thousand times because it just keeps throwing away its scratch paper.
Throwing away the scratch paper. That's a great way to put it.
Right.
Dynamic programming is simply the act of keeping the scratch paper.
Why?
The first time the computer figures out the best way to multiply matrices 1 through 5, it saves that answer in a table.
The next time it encounters that exact subproblem, it doesn't do the math again. It just looks up the answer.
That makes total sense for an abstract math problem.
But Fliction points out that this exact same algorithmic structure applies to things that aren't abstract equations at all.
Yes, it scales to the physical world.
Let's look at the classic shortest path algorithms, like Dykstra or Bellman Ford.
These are literally the math used in our GPS systems.
I always visualize Dykstra as dropping a pebble in a pond.
Let's expand on that visualization because it maps really perfectly to the math.
When you want to find the shortest path from your house to a coffee shop, the algorithm doesn't just draw a straight line.
Because there are buildings in the way.
Right. It starts at your house, the source, and propagates outward in all directions simultaneously, exactly like a ripple in a pond.
And as the ripple expands, it hits the street intersections closest to my house first.
Yes. And as the wavefront washes over an intersection, the algorithm locks in the absolute shortest distance to that specific intersection.
Why does it lock it in?
Because of optimal substructure.
Any destination further out that uses this intersection must use this locked-in shortest path to get there.
There's no faster way.
Right. The wave just continues outward.
Exactly. Finalizing the optimal path to every single point on the map until the wave finally washes over the coffee shop.
So the algorithm is essentially building this gradient of distance across the entire city.
And it's not just physical maps either. The text brings up sequence alignment.
This is the math used in genetics, like the Smith-Waterman algorithm.
Right. For DNA.
Yeah.
When scientists are trying to compare two strands of DNA to see how closely related they are, they aren't looking at a physical map at all.
No. They are looking at biological information. But the mathematical structure is totally identical.
How so?
In sequence alignment, the state isn't a street intersection. It's a specific cell in a grid that represents the alignment of two small prefixes of DNA.
To find the optimal alignment of a long sequence, the algorithm looks at the optimal alignment of slightly shorter snippets, checking for matches or mutations or gaps.
It's building the global biological relationship out of optimal local biological relationships.
Precisely.
But the example from the text that totally threw me, like, really messed with my head was the egg drop problem.
Oh, that's a classic.
It's a famous computer science puzzle.
And Fliction uses it to reveal something incredibly profound about what a state actually is.
Let's set up the puzzle for the listener.
You have a building with, say, 100 floors.
And you have a certain number of identical eggs.
Let's say you have two eggs.
All right.
Your goal is to find out the highest floor from which you can drop an egg without it breaking.
But you want to figure this out using the absolute minimum number of drops in the worst-case scenario.
It's such a brilliant problem.
If you only had one egg, you'd be forced to start at floor one and just go up one by one.
Right.
Because if you guess floor 50 and it breaks, you're out of eggs and you don't know the answer.
Exactly.
If it breaks on floor 50 one by one, you know the answer is 49.
But it literally took you 50 drops to find out.
But if you have multiple eggs, you can take bigger risks.
You might drop the first egg from floor 50 right away.
Right.
And if it breaks, you lost an egg.
Yeah.
But you instantly know the critical floor is somewhere between 1 and 49.
So you take your second, final egg and start at floor one.
And if the first egg survives the drop from 50, you still have two eggs.
And you know the critical floor is somewhere between 51 and 100.
Now, think about how dynamic programming actually solves this.
The algorithm needs to define a state to store in its memory table the scratch paper.
In the map problem, the state was a physical intersection.
In the DNA problem, the state was a biological sequence.
But in the egg drop problem, the state is defined purely by two numbers.
How many eggs you have left and how many untested floors remain.
And this is the part that completely blew my mind.
The text points out that this state is not a physical configuration of reality at all.
It's an epistemic configuration.
Let's clarify what epistemic means in this context, just so we don't lose anyone.
Epistemology is the study of knowledge.
Right.
So an epistemic state refers to a measure of what you know versus what you do not know.
The number of untested floors represents the size of your ignorance.
It's your remaining uncertainty.
And then the eggs.
The number of eggs represents your experimental budget.
It's the resources you have left to physically probe reality and gain knowledge.
So when the dynamic programming algorithm is crunching the numbers for the egg drop puzzle,
it is mathematically calculating the optimal path to collapse human uncertainty down to zero.
Exactly.
And it does this using the exact same Bellman equation it used to find the coffee shop and
to align the DNA strands.
And this, this right here is where the standard computer science textbook completely fails
us and why Flixian wrote this entire monograph.
This raises an important question, doesn't it?
It really does.
If dynamic programming is just a neat little trick programmers invented to save memory on a silicon
chip, why in the world does the exact same mathematical equation flawlessly describe physical distances
on a map, biological mutations in genetics, and the abstract epistemic bounds of human knowledge?
It's uncanny.
The standard account tells us what the code is doing.
It totally fails to explain why it works across every conceivable domain of reality.
The universality of the math strongly suggests it is not a human invention at all.
It's a discovery.
A discovery.
Yeah.
It suggests that dynamic programming is capturing a fundamental underlying geometry of how systems
evolve.
Think of it this way.
If the manual for your kitchen toaster perfectly describes the orbital mechanics of a distant
galaxy, you have to admit you aren't just looking at a toaster manual anymore.
Huh.
That's a perfect way to put it.
And that realization is what launches us out of standard computer science and into the
absolute heart of Flicksheen's paper.
This brings us to the RSVP paradigm shift.
RSVP stands for the Relativistic Scalar Vector Plenum.
Okay.
That's a lot of words.
It is.
This is the unifying theoretical framework Flicksheen has constructed.
The central premise is that we need to entirely stop thinking about computers executing discrete
lines of code.
Instead, both physical systems and computational algorithms evolve over what the text calls
admissible manifolds.
Let's break down admissible manifolds so you, the listener, can actually visualize this.
A manifold, broadly speaking, is just a mathematical space, right?
Like a landscape.
Yes.
Think of it as a vast, multidimensional terrain that represents every possible state a system
could conceivably be in.
But the key word here is admissible.
Allowed.
Correct.
Not every path across this terrain is actually possible.
If you are a physical particle, some paths violate the conservation of energy.
If you are an AI playing chess, some paths violate the rules of the game.
If you are a biological organism, some paths lead immediately to starvation and death.
So the admissible trajectories are the paths that obey the structural constraints of the
system.
They are the paths that keep the system viable, alive, functioning.
They are the allowed futures.
Okay.
So reality is a landscape of allowed futures.
To navigate this landscape, fliction establishes what they call a fundamental identification.
The text takes the three boring standard components of a dynamic programming algorithm and maps them directly onto physical fields in this RSVP universe.
This trinity is really the core of the whole paper.
Let's take these one by one.
First, the value function.
In standard DP, the value function is just the score you assign to a state, right?
High score is good.
Low score is bad.
Fliction maps this to a physical field called the scalar accessibility potential, represented
by the Greek letter phi.
The massive shift here is moving from a discrete number in a spreadsheet to a continuous physical
field.
In RSVP, phi isn't just a point system for winning a video game.
It is a physical geometric measure of how much of the future remains open, accessible, and favorable
to the system.
So if I am in a state with a high phi, it means I am standing on a vantage point where
I have a massive horizon of highly rewarding possibilities ahead of me.
But if I am in a state with a low phi, my future is constrained.
I'm backed into a corner.
Yes.
The value function is a literal landscape of potential energy.
Now let's look at the second component.
In a computer algorithm, you have a policy.
Right.
This is the logical rule, the iphon statement that tells the computer what action to take
next.
Fliction maps the policy to the vector flow field, or v.
So the scalar field phi is the shape of the landscape, and the vector field v is the actual
direction of movement.
Exactly.
The policy is no longer seen as a line of code.
It is a physical tangent vector.
It is the directional arrow pointing exactly along the path that most efficiently navigates
the gradient of the potential field phi.
And optimal policy is just the natural flow of a system seeking the highest accessible
future.
Yes.
And the third part of the trinity in dp, we have the admissibility volume.
That's the sheer number of viable paths left to take.
Fliction maps this to the entropy field, represented by s.
It is the logarithmic volume of open futures.
We have to be very careful here to distinguish between the value phi and the entropy s, because
they are not the same thing at all.
Not at all.
You could be in a state with an incredibly high phi, meaning there is an astronomically
high reward available to you, but getting that reward requires you to walk a tightrope
over an active volcano.
Right.
There is only one specific narrow path to get the prize.
Yeah.
If you deviate by an inch, you die.
Exactly.
That state has high phi, meaning high reward potential, but extremely low s, very low entropy,
very few viable paths.
But conversely, you could be in a state with a mediocre phi, but massive s.
Yes.
Like, you might not be on the path to becoming a billionaire, but you have thousands of different
safe, acceptable, middle-class career paths available to you.
High entropy means high flexibility.
You have room to breathe.
Here's where it gets really interesting.
I want to offer an analogy here to help you, the listener, really lock this trinity into
your mind.
Imagine a massive mountain and it's pouring rain.
Oh.
The water is trying to find its way down.
The mountain itself, the physical height, the slopes, the dips and valleys, that is the
scalar accessibility potential find.
It dictates the potential energy and the shape of the landscape.
Perfect.
The actual direction the water naturally rushes based on gravity, the specific currents cutting
through the dirt that is the vector flow field, it's the policy the water follows.
Right.
And finally, how wide the river channel is, how much room the water has to slosh around
left and right, exploring the banks while still generally flowing downward.
That is the entropy field, S.
That analogy holds up beautifully under the math.
When a dynamic programming algorithm runs, it is essentially acting as a divine cartographer.
Oh, I like that.
It is simultaneously calculating the exact topographical shape of the mountain, which is phi, defining
the precise currents of the rivers, which is V, and measuring the exact width
of the floodplains, which is S.
There is another concept from standard DP that gets translated into physical reality here.
And it's a concept that always felt completely artificial to me.
Which one?
The discount factor, represented by gamma.
In computer science or economics, you use a discount factor because a reward today is worth
more than a reward tomorrow.
Right.
It's a financial concept.
A dollar today is better than a dollar in 10 years.
But Flitchin claims gamma isn't a financial hack at all.
It's a physical property of the universe.
Let's look at the mechanics of that.
In the RSVP framework, the discount factor represents the system's coherence length.
Coherence length.
Meaning, like, how far into the future the system can actually maintain its structural integrity.
Precisely.
If a system has a gamma approaching 1, it means the system is highly stable.
It can plan for the distant future because its structural coherence extends far through time.
It cares about rewards that are a hundred steps away.
But if a system is highly volatile, its gamma drops towards zero.
It completely discounts tomorrow because tomorrow is entirely unpredictable.
Its coherence length has shrunk.
It only optimizes for immediate short-term survival.
So when a programmer arbitrarily types gamma equals 0.9 into their code, they aren't just tweaking a financial parameter.
They are mathematically simulating the temporal decay wave of a physical system.
The algorithm is physically behaving like a decaying wave in the scalar vector plenum.
This realization requires us to fundamentally shift our entire perspective.
If a state in a computer program is actually a geometric position in a continuous physical field, we have to completely rethink what computation actually is.
We do.
When a computer remembers a number in a dynamic programming table, it isn't just etching data onto a silicon hard drive, which raises the question, what is memory in a geometric universe?
And that question leads us to what is arguably the most profound philosophical assertion in Fliction's monograph.
It's the concept of memoization as ontological compression.
Let's define the terms for the listener.
Memoization is a computer science term.
It basically means making a memo.
When an algorithm calculates a complex equation, instead of throwing the answer away, it writes it down in a lookup table.
The next time it encounters that exact equation, it doesn't do the math.
It just reads the memo.
It's caching.
That is the functional definition, yes.
But Fliction says this is not just caching data.
It is ontological compression.
It is ontological meaning related to the fundamental nature of being, of reality itself.
How does saving a number in a table equate to compressing reality?
To understand this, we have to explore Fliction's concept of dynamic equivalence.
Let's build a thought experiment.
Yeah.
Imagine you and I agree to meet at a specific coffee shop at exactly noon.
We both arrive on time, and we both have exactly $10 in our pockets.
Right.
But our histories of how we got there are radically different.
Okay.
Let's say I woke up late, I rushed to the subway, almost lost my wallet, and then I sprinted the last three blocks.
Sounds stressful.
And let's say I woke up early, took a leisurely stroll through a park, stopped to read a book, and walked into the shop.
Okay, so our past trajectories are vastly different.
Very different.
But from the exact moment we're both standing at the counter, from the perspective of our future admissibility, does our past matter?
Well, no.
We both have $10.
We can both buy the exact same cup of coffee.
We have the same options of where to sit.
Exactly.
Our future admissibility sets our phi and s fields going forward are mathematically identical.
Focliction defines this by saying our two distinct histories are dynamically equivalent.
Because the future possibilities are identical, the pasts are mathematically indistinguishable going forward.
And here is the ontological leap.
The universe, or the optimal algorithm, does not merely forget our distinct histories out of computational convenience.
The math suggests that the past histories literally cease to exist as independent geometric entities.
Wait, really?
Yes.
The two distinct timelines collapse into a single point.
That point is the state.
The state is defined purely as the equivalence class of all histories that share the exact same future.
Hold on.
Let me push back on this.
Because this sounds like we are saying reality literally deletes the past.
Are you saying that when a computer uses a lookup table, when it memoizes a value, it is not taking a clever programming shortcut.
It is accurately simulating a physical truth that reality actively compresses redundant timelines.
The math actually supports this literal interpretation.
Flitchin provides a rigorous proof called the compression theorem.
How does that work?
Think about the sheer volume of history.
If you track every single possible branching choice in a complex system, the tree of histories explodes exponentially.
It goes to infinity so fast that no universe could contain the information.
The combinatorial explosion.
Right.
But if you apply the rule of dynamic equivalence, compressing every history that shares a future into a single node, that infinite exploding tree collapses into a polynomial state space.
It shrinks into a manageable geometric object.
The universe survives by constantly compressing its own history.
Yes.
And when this compression happens, the timelines don't just vanish into the ether.
When the branching histories are pruned and collapsed, they leave behind what Flitchin calls a projection residue.
What exactly is a projection residue?
Think of it as a permanent geometric imprint left on the admissibility field.
The specific numbers stored in the dynamic programming table, the value phi and the tangent vector v, are the projection residues.
They are the dense, aggregated footprint of all the collapsed pasts that led to that specific configuration of future potential.
Let me try a physical analogy.
If you take a flat piece of paper and you fold it in half, you are compressing it.
If you unfold the paper, the paper is flat again, but the crease remains.
The crease is permanent.
The crease is the projection residue.
That is a brilliant way to visualize it.
The memorization table in a computer, the lookup table, is essentially a map of the universe's creases.
It is a record of where reality has folded its own history to maintain computational viability.
But if these states are just compressed creases of future possibility, how do they relate to each other?
A table of numbers is discrete, but reality is continuous.
How do we stitch all of these folded pieces of space back together without tearing the fabric?
Answering that requires a transition into a very specific, highly advanced branch of mathematics.
This is where Fliction introduces the geometry of optimization.
I am going to act as the proxy for the listener right now, because when I read this section of the paper, I felt a genuine sense of dread.
It's definitely dense.
The text introduces sheaf theory.
It talks about stalks, germs, and cohomological obstructions.
Let's please ground this.
What on earth is a sheaf, and why do we need it to understand an algorithm?
It is notoriously intimidating jargon, but the underlying concept is actually very intuitive.
Sheaf theory is just a mathematical language designed to solve one specific problem.
How do you take a bunch of local, isolated pieces of data and perfectly glue them together to form a globally consistent picture?
Like assembling a jigsaw puzzle.
Exactly like a jigsaw puzzle.
Imagine you have a thousand pieces of a puzzle.
Each piece only contains local data.
One piece has a bit of blue sky.
Another piece has the tip of a green leaf.
Sheaf theory defines the mathematical rules for how these pieces can be connected.
The edges of the puzzle pieces are what mathematicians call restriction maps.
They dictate how the data on one piece must perfectly match the data on the adjacent piece.
And if every single piece obeys the gluing rules with its immediate neighbors, you can confidently assemble the entire global image.
Yes.
And Flickia makes a startling identification here.
The dynamic programming table, that simple grid of numbers the computer is using, is literally a discretized admissibility sheaf.
Let's walk through how that works.
Every individual cell in the DP table is one piece of the puzzle.
It contains the local data about the future possibilities from that specific state.
But how do we know the cells connect properly?
How do we know?
The Bellman equation, the recursive formula we talked about in the beginning, is the gluing axiom.
It mathematically forces the local future data in cell A to perfectly match the local future data in cell B.
So when an algorithm finishes running, it hasn't just populated a spreadsheet.
It has successfully glued a thousand isolated puzzle pieces of possibility into a single, seamless, globally consistent field of action.
Precisely. It constructs a global manifold from local fragments.
Okay, but what happens when the puzzle pieces don't fit?
What if a problem is fundamentally unsolvable?
Like, if the rules of a game contradict themselves, or a computer gets stuck in an infinite loop?
This is where sheaf theory really proves its worth.
Fliction explains infeasibility, the inability to solve a problem through the lens of first sheaf cohomology, denoted mathematically as H1.
Co-homology. Another terrifying word.
Let's demystify it.
Co-homology is basically a tool to measure the holes, or topological twists, in a space.
If a problem has contradictory constraints, like an infinite loop, the local puzzle pieces might look perfectly fine in isolation.
When you try to put them together.
When you try to glue them all together, they twist. They refuse to lay flat.
Oh, like an M.C. Escher painting. The famous impossible staircase.
If you look at any single step on the staircase, it makes perfect sense.
The local geometry is fine. Step A leads up to step B.
Exactly.
But when you follow the steps all the way around, it forms a closed loop that completely contradicts gravity.
The Escher staircase is the ultimate visualization of non-trivial topology.
If the cohomology H1 is greater than zero, it means your space contains an Escher staircase.
There is a topological obstruction.
So the computer isn't just failing to find the answer.
Right. The problem isn't that your computer lacks the processing power to find the optimal path.
The problem is that the geometry of the constraints is fundamentally twisted.
A globally consistent, optimal value function cannot exist because the universe you built is structurally flawed.
That is mind-bending.
But what's even more fascinating is how Flixson uses this framework to bridge the gap between
discrete computer code and the continuous physics of the real world.
The paper dives into the Hamilton-Jacobe-Bellman equation, or HJB.
What's fascinating here is that the HJB equation is simply the continuous time version of Bellman's principle.
Instead of an algorithm jumping discreetly from cell A to cell B in a table,
imagine a system sliding smoothly along a continuous trajectory in space and time.
And Flixson points out that the HJB equation is structurally identical to the equations that govern classical mechanics.
Let's look at the mechanics of that.
Yeah.
In classical physics, Hamilton's principle function dictates that physical objects, like a thrown baseball,
will always move along a trajectory that minimizes action.
Action is just a physical measure of energy over time.
So a baseball flying through the air is mathematically minimizing its action in the exact same way
a GPS algorithm minimizes the distance on a map.
It is the exact same equation.
The baseball is continuously calculating its optimal policy vector v to navigate the gravitational potential field phi.
That's wild.
But the connection runs even deeper, straight into the microscopic realm.
If you take the Hamilton-Jacobe equation and apply a specific mathematical transformation to it,
a logarithmic transform, you produce the Schrödinger equation.
Wait, wait, slow down.
You're jumping from a thrown baseball to quantum mechanics.
How does a math trick turn a baseball into a quantum probability wave?
It's all about how the system handles uncertainty and paths.
In classical mechanics, the baseball takes one single definitive optimal path.
Right.
But in quantum mechanics, a particle doesn't take one path.
It explores all possible paths simultaneously.
The logarithmic transform takes the single optimal trajectory of the baseball
and smears it into a probability distribution.
It smears it out.
Yeah.
The probability amplitude of a quantum electron is mathematically equivalent to the exponential of the action potential.
So, an electron navigating through a double-slit experiment isn't just bouncing around randomly.
It is effectively executing a continuous dynamic programming algorithm,
optimizing its admissibility over the quantum manifold.
That is the direct, unavoidable implication of the mathematics.
Dynamic programming in a computer, the classical mechanics of a baseball,
and the quantum mechanics of an electron are all expressions of the exact same recursive geometry.
They're all the same thing.
They only differ in their regularity assumptions and how they actually handle uncertainty.
Which brings up a really important point.
Reality isn't perfectly predictable.
There is thermal noise, there is wind, there are random quantum fluctuations.
How does this geometric framework handle randomness?
The text addresses this using the Feynman-Cack formula.
This formula connects diffusion processes, which is the mathematical term for random, jittering noise,
directly to optimal control.
How does adding random noise change the admissibility landscape?
Think back to the mountain analogy.
If there is no noise, the paths are rigid.
A cliff is a cliff.
Right.
But if you introduce random noise, it softens the hard boundaries of what is admissible.
It smears the probability mass over the state space.
So instead of a hard wall where a path becomes instantly impossible, the wall becomes a gradient.
Yes.
The random noise allows the system to probabilistically explore regions near the boundaries of admissibility
that would otherwise be completely forbidden.
The value function phi becomes an expectation, a weighted average over all possible random, jittering trajectories.
It defines how a physical system can optimize its future even when the landscape itself is constantly vibrating and shifting beneath it.
If this mathematics governs the rigid logic of static computer programs, the classical arcs of baseballs, and the jittering diffusion of quantum particles,
does it also apply to a system that doesn't know the landscape?
That's the logical next step.
Yeah.
What happens if you drop an agent into a maze without a map, and it has to actively learn how to survive?
If the math holds up, this bridges us directly into the realm of artificial intelligence, specifically reinforcement learning.
Reinforcement learning, or RL, is the branch of AI where an agent learns exclusively through trial and error.
It doesn't have the dynamic programming table pre-calculated.
It has no map.
Exactly.
It just takes actions, receives rewards or punishments from the environment, and updates its internal logic.
The paper specifically examines Q-learning, which is a foundational RL algorithm.
Normally, Q-learning is explained very simply.
The AI takes a step, gets a point, and updates its guess of how good that step was.
Right.
But through the RSVP lens, Fliction describes Q-learning as adaptive admissibility stabilization.
Let's translate that.
The mechanism here relies on something called entropy descent.
In the RSVP framework, the Bellman equation isn't just updating a discrete cell in a spreadsheet.
It acts as a recursive wave that washes back and forth over the agent's internal terrain.
Walk me through a concrete example.
Imagine the AI is a little robot navigating a maze.
Okay.
The robot has an internal map of what it thinks the accessibility potential field phi looks like.
It thinks stepping forward is a high-value action, so it steps forward.
Makes sense.
But instead of open space, it bumps into a physical wall.
It thought it was stepping onto solid ground, but reality completely disagreed.
This collision creates an admissibility discrepancy.
It is the mathematical delta between the AI's internal projection of the future and the true physical constraints of the environment.
So what does the algorithm do with that discrepancy?
It uses it to perform gradient descent.
The Q-learning algorithm takes the error from that wall collision and sends a mathematical wave rippling backward through the robot's internal map, altering the slopes and valleys of its internal phi field.
It redraws the map.
Yes.
The AI rolls down the slope of its own error.
This wave washes back and forth with every action the robot takes, recursively updating the field until the AI's internal map of potential perfectly matches the true physical reality of the maze.
The wave stabilizes.
That perfectly explains the actor-critic architecture that Flixion highlights.
For you listening, actor-critic is a hugely popular model in modern AI where you use two separate neural networks to solve a problem.
Flixion calls this a decomposed field dynamic.
Yes.
It's a very elegant way to look at it.
Let me try to build an analogy for this.
Yeah.
Imagine you are in the passenger seat of a car in a foreign city.
You have the GPS map on your phone.
You are the critic.
You are building the scalar field phi.
You are looking at the terrain, calculating the high-value areas, finding the optimal route.
The person actually holding the steering wheel is the actor.
They are following the vector flow field V.
They don't look at the map.
They just steer based on your instructions.
That maps precisely to the architecture.
The critic and the actor are independent but tightly coupled.
And they update each other in real time.
Yeah.
If the driver, the actor, turns onto a street and sees it's blocked by construction, they experience an admissibility discrepancy.
They hit the wall.
Exactly.
They tell you, the mapmaker, the critic.
You update the map, you recursively alter the phi field, and then you give the driver a new tangent vector V to follow.
It is a continuous, real-time stabilization of the scalar and vector fields.
But the AI faces a fundamental problem while it navigates this unknown city, the exploration versus exploitation dilemma.
And Fliction brilliantly frames this dilemma using the third part of our trinity, the entropy field S.
Exploitation is when the AI acts greedily, right?
It knows a path that gives a decent reward, so it just takes that path over and over.
Yes.
In RSVP terms, exploitation is relentlessly ascending the gradient of the phi field.
The AI climbs the highest peak it can currently see.
But the danger of pure exploitation is getting trapped on a local hill.
Exactly.
The AI might climb a tiny mound and stop, completely unaware that there is a massive mountain of rewards hidden in the fog just a few miles away.
Because it never explored the fog.
Right.
This is why modern AI uses maximum entropy RL.
In this mathematical setup, exploration is defined as the active maximization of the entropy field S.
Oh, wow.
The AI is explicitly programmed with a dual mandate.
Find the reward, but also seek out states that preserve the highest logarithmic volume of admissible futures.
It wants to keep its options open.
It values flexibility and freedom of movement as much as it values the actual price.
Yes.
And the balance between these two goals is mediated by a parameter called temperature.
If the temperature parameter is set high, the system prioritizes S over phi.
It explores wildly.
It acts almost randomly to ensure its entropy stays high and it maps the whole environment.
If the temperature is lowered, the system cools into pure exploitation, locking onto the phi gradient and rushing toward the known reward.
Okay.
Let's pause and just reflect on the magnitude of what we are discussing.
Mm-hmm.
We have established that AI agents use this recursive wave of entropy descent to navigate their environments, taking actions to keep their future entropy high and ascending their potential fields.
Yes.
And we've established this math perfectly mirrors the laws of physics.
So is this the exact same algorithm happening inside our own heads?
Because if the math applies to a quantum particle and an artificial neural network, why wouldn't it apply to the biological neural network of the human brain?
That is the exact threshold we cross in Section Sense Affliction's paper, Moving into Cognitive Science and the Philosophy of Mind.
The text introduces a radical theory of perception called Constraint Before Content.
Constraint Before Content.
The standard way we think about human perception is very linear.
We think, you know, my eyes take in raw photons, my visual cortex builds a 3D model of a coffee cup, that's the content,
and then my frontal lobe figures out what I can safely do with the cup without burning my hand.
Those are the constraints.
We think content comes first, constraints come second.
But Flixion says this is completely backwards.
Entirely backwards.
Flixion argues that the brain does not operate by processing raw sensory data to construct a neutral world model.
Instead, cognition is fundamentally the compression of incoming sensory trajectories to fit prior admissibility constraints.
Can you explain the actual mechanism of how that works in the brain?
The constraints do not filter the possibilities after the fact.
The constraints literally constitute the space of perception.
Wait, really?
Yes.
When you look at an object, your brain is instantly pattern matching the incoming light to stored admissibility residues,
the projection residues we discussed during memorization.
You do not see a ceramic cylinder containing hot brown liquid.
You instantly perceive a dynamically equivalent state of graspability and caffeine acquisition.
So when I look at the coffee cup, my brain isn't calculating the physics of the cup from scratch.
No.
It is just accessing the biological dynamic programming table.
It's looking up the memoized state.
Exactly.
Your brain perceives a world purely in terms of the phi and v fields that the objects afford you.
Infliction formalizes this mechanism in what they call aspect relegation theory.
Okay.
This provides a rigorous mathematical foundation for the famous psychological framework of system one and system two thinking.
Right.
The dual process theory.
System one is our fast, automatic, unconscious intuition.
System two is our slow, deliberate, analytical reasoning.
How does aspect relegation map to these systems?
In the RSV PDP framework, system two is the active, energy-intensive calculation of the Bellman recursion.
It is your brain slowly exploring a novel state space, calculating the gradients of phi and v from scratch.
Thinking really hard.
Yes.
Think back to your hook at the beginning of the show, learning to drive a car for the very first time.
Right.
When you are 16 years old, driving is exhausting.
You are hyper aware of the pressure on the gas pedal, the angle of the steering wheel, the cars and the mirrors.
You are consciously crunching all the variables.
Because your system two is actively generating the dynamic programming table, it is experiencing massive admissibility discrepancies and recursively stabilizing the fields.
But aspect relegation is the biological process of memoization.
Once your system two has stabilized an optimal driving trajectory through repeated practice, the brain collapses that history under dynamic equivalence.
It creates a permanent projection residue.
It folds the paper and makes the crease.
Yes.
And once that crease is formed, it is relegated to system one.
From that point on, when you encounter that state again, system one does no mathematical calculation.
It simply looks up the value in the biological DP table in constant time.
So when I experienced that phenomenon of driving home on autopilot, spacing out, and suddenly realizing I'm in my driveway with no memory of the trip, my brain literally was not thinking in the computational sense.
No, it wasn't.
I wasn't processing variables.
My system one was just chaining together projection residues from dynamically equivalent pasts.
It pulled a tangent vector V from the lookup table, and my hands just steered the wheel.
That is the exact mathematical reality of human habit and intuition under this theory.
Your brain irreversibly transformed the rich, exhausting history of learning to drive into a highly compressed, polynomial state space of automatic reactions.
If the brain is just a biological machine constantly running Duhlman recursions and memoizing the results into habits, what is consciousness?
The text makes a speculative but incredibly profound proposal here.
If we connect this to the bigger picture, it is perhaps the most ambitious claim in the monograph.
Fliction proposes that human consciousness, the actual subjective experience of being awake and aware, arises physically at the fixed point of the cognitive Bellman iteration.
Let me make sure I understand the mechanics of this.
The brain is constantly being bombarded by sensory data.
It is constantly running these recursive waves, trying to stabilize its internal model against the incoming reality.
It's calculating discrepancies.
Yes. The waves of entropy descent are constantly washing across the neural architecture, adjusting the scalar field phi.
And when does the thought actually become conscious?
When that recursive wave washes across the entire cognitive manifold and finally stabilizes.
When the mathematical delta reaches zero.
Zero.
When further application of the Bellman operator produces absolutely no change in the accessibility potential field.
That mathematically stabilized fixed point is the conscious thought.
Yeah.
A thought only becomes conscious when the entire distributed network of the brain basically agrees on the admissibility structure of the present moment.
That is breathtaking.
It really is.
It means consciousness isn't a magical spark.
It is the physical sensation of a global mathematical field reaching equilibrium.
It connects the deepest, most elusive mysteries of subjective experience directly to the fixed point theorems of functional analysis.
OK. We have scaled this geometry from the code in a computer to the quantum probability of an electron to an AI learning a maze to the biological fixed point of human consciousness.
We've covered a lot of ground.
We really have.
Now, we have to zoom out one final time.
If individual human minds operate by compressing and navigating these admissibility constraints, what happens when you put a billion of these minds together?
What happens when they interact in a shared society?
This brings us to the final analytical portion of the paper, political economy and extractive systems.
And I want to put a very clear disclaimer out there for you, the listener.
We are examining this strictly through the mathematical lens provided in the source text.
Fliction uses these equations to analyze economic policies purely as geometric constraint propagations.
We are not taking political sides here.
We are simply reporting how the math behaves when you scale it up to human societies.
That is the correct approach.
The core insight here is that in the RSVKTP model, macroeconomic institutions, things like property rights, legal regulations and financial markets,
are not viewed as abstract human concepts.
Mathematically, they are literal geometric constraints.
They define the admissibility structure of human trajectories.
They dictate the shape of the manifold we all live on.
They define which futures are physically and economically accessible to an agent and which ones are walled off by a hard boundary.
Infliction models specific economic phenomena by tracking how these boundaries shift.
A prime example is the mathematics of fiscal austerity.
Austerity, meaning severe government reductions in public spending, cutting social safety nets, reducing grants.
How does dynamic programming view austerity?
The text defines austerity mathematically as admissibility pruning.
When an institution cuts resources for vulnerable populations, it is geometrically severing the number of admissible projectories available to agents in precarious states.
It is artificially shrinking their entropy field, S.
And the really crucial mechanism the text exposes is that this pruning doesn't just affect the future.
It has a Bellman multiplier that propagates backward through time.
Let's ground this with a concrete example to show how this multiplier works.
Imagine a government announces that next year they are cutting all federal college grants for low-income students.
They have pruned the future.
But how does the Bellman multiplier alter the present?
If a high school junior hears that announcement today, they realize college is no longer an accessible state.
So they immediately drop out of their advanced placement classes and pick up a minimum wage job right now to help their family.
That is the Bellman recursion in action.
The future constraint physically altered their present tangent vector, V-eternal, by foreclosing a high-value future state.
The current value of the present state that might have transitioned into that future is mathematically reduced.
The wave washes backward.
The accessibility potential, FING, collapses across the entire economic manifold, altering the present behavior of millions of agents long before the cuts even take effect.
The mathematics show that the effects of pruning are never localized.
They geometrically collapse the accessibility of the entire system.
The text also applies this geometric analysis to digital algorithms, specifically taking aim at platform capitalism and social media feed architectures.
And it frames this dynamic as a literal conflict of fields.
We have to remember that the recommendation algorithms running major platforms are reinforcement learning agents.
They are actively executing Q-learning.
They are maximizing a specific reward function.
For a social media platform, the RL agent's accessibility potential is defined entirely by engagement metrics, screen time, and ad revenue.
Let's call the platform's potential field-fi platform.
Meanwhile, the human user navigating the platform is their own agent, with their own optimal states they are trying to reach, maybe finding useful information, connecting with a friend, or maintaining their mental well-being.
Let's call the user's potential field-fi user.
Fliction's analysis reveals that the platform's optimal policy, its vector flow field v-platform, is designed strictly to maximize phi-platform.
But mathematically, maximizing engagement often requires redirecting the user's trajectories away from the user's own optimal states.
Walk me through the mechanism of how the algorithm actually does that.
If the algorithm allows the user to find the information they need quickly, which maximizes phi-user, the user will close the app.
That reduces phi-platform.
Oh, I see.
Therefore, the algorithm must alter the user's environment to ensure the user stays trapped in a loop of high engagement, often by surfacing enraging or addictive content.
So the algorithm is essentially an extractive geometric system.
It mathematically forces a reduction in the user's admissibility entropy S, walling off their healthy exit paths in order to feed its own fixed point.
It bends the human's trajectory to keep them on the platform, even if that trajectory leads the user to a lower-value, highly constrained state in their own physical life.
It is geometry weaponized for attention.
The platform's optimization is mathematically admissibility-reducing for the user while being admissibility-expanding for the platform.
It is a zero-sum geometric extraction of entropy.
Wow.
So what does this all mean?
We have covered an immense, staggering amount of ground today.
We started by looking at a simple programming trick designed to save scratch paper on a 1950s computer.
And we ended up mapping the mathematical extraction of human attention by a digital algorithm.
It's a massive synthesis.
Let's summarize the journey we've taken.
Dynamic programming is not a line of code.
It is a universal geometric law, from the shortest path calculated on a GPS map,
to the probabilistic jittering of a quantum particle,
to the memoized unconscious habits firing in our brains as we drive home,
to the gravitational pull of econotic constraints on a society.
Reality is a singular process of recursive admissibility.
Beautifully said.
We are all navigating a scalar vector plenum.
Every system, conscious or inert, is trying to climb the gradient of the potential field,
trying to keep its future trajectories open,
trying to maximize its entropy so it doesn't get completely trapped.
The convergence of these frameworks is really profound.
Whether it is an artificial neural network learning to navigate a maze,
an electron finding its path through a slit,
or a human mind achieving consciousness through the stabilization of a cognitive field,
the underlying architecture is identical.
It is all the geometry of optimization.
Which leaves us staring at an incredibly provocative implication.
Yeah.
If the math holds true, it changes how we view literally everything.
I want you, the listener, to think about the ultimate conclusion of this framework.
If every conscious human agent, every physical quantum particle,
every artificial intelligence, and every macroeconomic system
is blindly executing a Bellman operator to recursively stabilize its own future admissibility,
then the universe is not a collection of separate, independent objects bumping into each other in the void.
It is a single, massive, overlapping dynamic program.
Reality itself is continuously running an optimization algorithm,
folding its history, and solving for the most admissible future.
But if the entire universe is solving a single, massive optimization problem,
who set the initial reward function, what is reality optimizing for?
That is the question that's going to keep me up tonight.
Something for all of us to think about the next time we're driving on autopilot.
Until next time.